hey everyone thanks for listening to The
Grow Your Life podcast my name is Jeremy
microkowski on this podcast I'll talk
about ways for coaches trainers and
mentors to grow their business and make
more money online
now today I want to talk about a break
free from the victim mentality and
before you start thinking that I'm gonna
go victim blaming calling them names
things like that and and being rude and
mean to people that are victims of harm
and Trauma no not at all I've
experienced a lot of trauma in my life
and I have healed through it but I
suffered from the victim mentality for a
while and it kept me from my goals it
kept me from making the kind of money
that I want to make and so I truly
believe
that and honestly this is inspired by
somebody that I saw on social media
that I have seen sort of a revolving
door in their life I hope they listen to
this podcast she tells me she listens to
it but I see a revolving door in their
life of
I'm a victim of people hurting me and I
am powerless in this okay and so a I
just want to acknowledge
leaders need to be wise with how they
lead people
um you know it's funny I was terrified
and shuttered when I started this
podcast because I knew that I wasn't a
great leader but I knew that I would be
leading people and now I I have a lot of
confidence that I've gotten so much
better at coaching people listening
um
our clients are getting great results a
ton of people tell me like that that
they that they see my heart kindness and
compassion and everything that I say and
and if you've followed me for a while
you notice that maybe that hasn't been
I've always come across for a while
um that's my own growth in my own
journey and so I've gone through therapy
for the last two years
um I've spent time if you listen to the
podcast episode a couple weeks back
using even chat CBT to help me uncover
new things and I'm telling you in the
last like couple weeks I've had some
massive breakthroughs just by using chat
CPT to help me uncover areas of my life
and so that's what I want to just
encourage you with though is how do we
break free from the victim mentality and
I'm going to use our trusty friend chat
GPT to kind of help us with this you
might you might groan if you hear that
first off if you're groaning because you
think that AI is not smart enough to
give you good advice why are you
googling things why are you listening to
podcasts why are you on social media why
are you even on YouTube the algorithms
are showing you content that's relevant
chat gbt is just an another algorithm
that gives you relevant content so let's
think about it from that perspective and
I'm going to compare it to a few other
uh AI platforms as well because honestly
we do a lot with AI here and so I'm
trying to integrate it more and more
into my podcasting into my everyday life
into the things that I do so let's let's
talk about this let's ask chat GPT just
a little bit to explain uh the victim
mentality
what is the victim mentality
we'll just start there
and I'm also going to ask uh Google's
Bard which is another AI platform
and we're going to ask
um Microsoft because you know what
why not
let's see what all three of these come
up with if they come up with some sort
of different answers Okay so
Google's barred was the quickest
and you can Google it as well
a victim mentality is a thought process
of a person who sees themselves as a
victim of circumstances beyond their
control
people with a victim mentality often
feel powerless hopeless and resentful
they may blame others for their problem
and refuse to take responsibility in
their own lives
the victim mentality can be a difficult
habit to break I'm telling you just for
myself it was difficult to break because
I was constantly looking for other
people to show up for me and I wasn't
showing up for myself
with time whenever people can learn to
overcome it you want to at first off you
want to identify it the first step in
overcoming it is identifying it take
responsibility take personal
responsibility set goals towards it
surround yourself with positive people
and getting help obviously okay I want
to dive deeper into identifying the
victim mentality how do you identify
the victim mentality
in yourself
okay this would be a great follow-up
question for all three of these
platforms just to see what they what
they generate
victim mentality is an acquired
personality trait where they tend to
recognize and consider themselves a
victim of negative actions and behave in
the case contrary to actual evidence
that's that's what Wikipedia says
that some when somebody can't accept
responsibility or admit their part in
bad things that have happened instead
they constantly blame others in their
life
according to WebMD you can look for
these signs you blame others in your
life you think life is out to get you is
out against you you have trouble coping
with problems in your life you feel
stuck in life you feel attacked when
somebody tries to offer helpful feedback
by the way I have still felt this
recently
this is actually powerful for me
realizing that that behavior right there
is a victim mentality
very interesting
I learned something every time I do this
stuff like this
external locus of control constantly
blaming others feeling powerless
lack of responsibility you know a great
book just on this topic that I read over
the last couple of years was
daring greatly
daring greatly by brene Brown
okay
and so for instance
can you provide some passages from
this is what I love with Chachi Boutique
from daring greatly by Renee Brown
as they relate to the above
topic
we'll ask
Yep this one pulled up kind of the same
thing you often feel like you're a
victim of circumstances outside of your
control you blame others you feel
powerless you're hopeless for your
future okay
so that's how you can identify if you
have the victim mentality as you is you
act hopeless
for the future you act like other things
outside of your control are responsible
for why your life is where it's at
and again if you're somebody who's
experienced trauma I'm going to just
pause here
hey if this triggered you too much you
probably weren't a good fit to listen to
my podcast or even be a part of my
programs and follow me because
we talk about tough stuff we talk about
hard things
and
what I love is we can use AI as like a
co-host a little bit I would love to
actually have an AI co-host that I could
talk to
you just gave me an idea for the podcast
that'd be awesome I might look into
doing something like that if we can
anyways
that's just my brain is like spinning on
that topic
trauma happens
abuse happens
horrible things have happened in our
lives
people are victims
of terrible things
the victim mentality is something
completely different
is where you blame why your life isn't
the way it is on everything else around
you on other people
on things outside of your control and
you believe
that you have no ability no say to
create and design your life
that was how I was living for a while
thinking that I had no ability and no
say in my life
those other people's fault
yeah
why I wasn't experiencing the life that
I wanted
I was blaming my mom I was blaming
people uh past clients uh prospects I
literally remember a prospect
on a sales call had said something to me
and I played the victim mentality card
for two years through therapy
as an excuse for why I couldn't succeed
so we gotta break this I'm telling you
for me in my life what has helped me
make the most amount of money is not
playing the victim oh I got people that
come after me they say things they might
even be attacking me
it's my choice to play the victim or not
okay let's take a look at this I love
this just some passages from from brene
Brown's book daring greatly Darren
greatly focuses on vulnerability and
embracing him for Perfections while it
doesn't necessarily focus on the victim
mentality it offers valuable insight to
help shift our mindset from feeling like
a victim vulnerability is not winning or
losing it's showing up it's Having the
courage to show up and be seen when we
have no control over the outcome
it's not weakness it's our greatest
measure of Courage
to me the clearest indication that we're
not embracing vulnerability is that
we're trying to control and manage it
when we start comparing our
vulnerability
shame needs three things to grow secrecy
silence and judgment
when something shaming happens we keep
it locked up at festers and it grows
and it consumes us
by acknowledging our experiences we can
transform from victimhood and
helplessness into a sense of empowerment
and connection
vulnerability is not weakness it's the
birthplace of courage and innovation
and so those are some just some quotes
from the book I'm sorry I couldn't find
any relevant passages yeah so Bing
couldn't find it but
powerlessness really is kind of the root
area
the root issue
that that we're dealing with
is that we feel like we are powerless to
everything that's going on around us and
outside of us
and that we have to sit back until
situations in our life change and align
and come into alignment so that we can
move forward it takes a choice just to
stop doing that but that choice is very
difficult
I struggled to make that choice until I
really worked through
and started to heal from some of these
traumas some of these pains some of
these beliefs some of these ideas
you know I used to have this thing and
and sometimes it still affects me that
unless I perfectly articulate myself on
a topic I should keep my mouth shut
and what that did was that made me be
silent when I make podcast episodes that
may be silent when I do content
I was afraid to talk about the things
that were inside of me because I didn't
feel like they were good enough to bring
out and so I was a victim of the
Judgment of other people in my life and
I was operating out of this mentality
that other people's opinions if they
don't like me I have to submit to them
and I have to obey them
and I had something happen
two months ago
I can point this out
I had I had I had somebody write me and
tell me that I was the scum of the Earth
the most vile person they'd ever met
all because I decided to change my
business model to where I'm no longer
answering direct messages
but they felt that as a coach
that made me
a huckster
and an evil person
and I played the victim in my mindset to
their opinion
and let it defeat me
and so
some things that we have to do we have
to do a
we have to cultivate resilience in our
life and strength and realize hey you're
stronger than what you're experiencing
in your life around you
you're stronger than just what's going
on
in your life
see here's the thing
we're often afraid to put ourselves out
there because of what other people
might do
to us
because we're playing the victim we
can't be vulnerable and we can't operate
invulnerability
because otherwise
we could lose everything we worked so
hard for because we're clinging so
tightly to some version of our life that
we imagined how things should go and
because we're powerless we're hanging on
to it so tightly so that we don't lose
the dream that we have
and that my friends is a cycle that
literally perpetuates
the victim mentality
I'm asking chat gbt this how does
not letting go
perpetuate the victim mentality
and this is so key because so many of us
do this
dwelling on our past constantly
revisiting past events that keep you
stuck in a negative cycle
we end up reinforcing our negative
beliefs by holding on to past
experiences we don't let go of negative
past relationships we start to believe
that we're Unworthy of love from other
people or that people will always
mistreat us this fuels the victim
mentality
we prevent ourselves from growing we
miss out on growth opportunities because
we're stuck in feelings of helplessness
and victimhood I was stopping myself
from growing
in my life in business because I was not
allowing myself to grow because I was in
the victimhood so much that that became
my identity
and that cycle of blame
and victimization
that's what keeps us stuck
you know one of the most powerful things
that you can do to help you if you're
dealing with the victim mentality is to
journal what you're feeling
as to write it out Journal it out what
are you going through what are you
dealing with what are you feeling
at any given moment in time
how does journaling
help with this
listen I get it I know some of you are
like you do not like that I'm doing this
that's fine
you might want to ask yourself though
why you don't like it
like what is so
about me using chat GPT like this
journaling can help increase
self-awareness
it encourages introspection
self-reflection
emotional processing
it helps you identify patterns and
that's the key if we can identify
patterns and triggers
in our victim mentality
[Music]
it no longer
has the ability to run our lives
Bing isn't super helpful
at some of these prompts but
Bard and chat gbt are pretty cool
I'm gonna turn Bing off
here's how you can identify patterns in
your thoughts and emotions keep a
journal
track your thoughts and emotions over
time track when you get triggered I do
this I did this for the last two years
any time that I was in a situation so
what I have is I have what I call like
my Baseline I'm happy
I'm I'm productive I'm in the mindset
and the mental state that
is the healthiest for me okay any time
that I would go outside of that to where
it felt significantly different than my
happiest state of mind and my most
productive state of mind I would journal
what am I thinking what am I feeling
what am I reacting to what situation
just happened
okay
and then I would identify those triggers
something else that's helped me yes is
meditation practices and then working
with a therapist what I did was I would
take all of those triggers and I would
bring it to my therapist when we would
talk we would go over what those are and
so we would have sort of a a cluster of
the same emotion the same reaction the
same issue manifesting in five different
ways
I was just coaching a client two weeks
ago where
I asked her three separate instances
where she felt a certain way
as it relates to her business her family
and her childhood and they were
identical situations that manifested in
some very
different ways and it contributed to her
victim mentality it contributed to her
feeling like everybody is out to get her
and her belief is that she's a warrior
and that she's strong and powerful but
at the same time what's coming out of
her mouth is everybody's unfair to me
nobody likes me it's it's everybody
else's fault and so by reframing that
and saying is that really fair to expect
other people
to show up for you in the way that you
desire them to is that really fair to
expect other people
to be responsible for your life and to
many people who operate out of the
victim mentality they think it is
usually it's related to a lack of
boundaries
and it's because we end up taking on
responsibility for other peoples
emotions and see this is one of the root
issues of the victim mentality
often related to people pleasing we end
up taking responsibility for other
people's feelings and emotions
how is the pattern of taking
responsibility
for other people's feelings and emotions
related to the victim
mentality this is going to be an
interesting response
see we're diving deep in here and I want
to see just what some of these responses
are so taking responsibility for other
people's emotions can be related in
several ways while the two patterns seem
distinct they actually both lack healthy
boundaries and their distorted belief in
personal control
so what it is is by taking both taking
responsibility for others emotions and
the victim mentality lack personal
boundaries in both scenarios the
eventual the individual struggles to
differentiate between their own emotions
and those of other people
and it's rooted in codependency taking
responsibility for other people's
emotions leads to codependent
relationships
constantly sacrificing themselves for
other people so here's what ends up
happening if you're somebody who
if you're somebody I'm gonna say it out
loud into the into the microphone
if you're somebody who
expects
other people that take care of you and
blames other people and you're
constantly sacrificing yourself for
others you expect the same level of
appreciation and support to what you
give to other people and that's just not
fair in life and so if you're operating
out of codependency
there's this distorted sense of control
to where we end up taking responsibility
for other people's emotions and then we
end up playing a victim when they don't
respond the way that we expect them to
the way that we would if we were them
and we end up projecting what we think
they should do in the situation and then
that is what perpetuates the victim
mentality
because we wouldn't do that thing if we
were them
we wouldn't show up in that way we
wouldn't do what they did to us if we
were them and so we end up believing
that everybody else thinks and operates
the same way that we do and this
perpetuates
the victim mentality
[Music]
and copy this into both of these
taking responsibility for other people's
feelings and emotions relates to the
victim mentality you need to set
boundaries learn to say no focus on
yourself
you know
I understand your point it's important
to remember that we're all different and
we have different needs and expectations
we can't control our people's actions
and we expect other people to take care
of us and appreciate us the same way we
care for them we're setting ourselves up
for disappointment
if you're struggling with codependency
seek professional help it's a great book
on codependency called codependent
no more and I would highly recommend
that you check it out
that you read it
to take a look at it
how to stop controlling others and start
caring for yourself
it's an amazing book
that's all about this topic of the the
never-ending drama that we experience in
our lives trying to be codependent with
other people
let's go over here
oh it looks like it uh it cleared the
the prompt
so we're done using that one
it seems you've highlighted a connection
between codependency and the victim
mentality indeed when individuals expect
others to take care of them and assume
responsibility they develop unrealistic
expectations about how others should
behave so this is what I was dealing
with I had unrealistic expectations
about how other people should behave in
my opinion
I was projecting my own beliefs on other
people
I had a perceived lack of appreciation
from others
that created this victimization
so to break free for this cycle and
overcome it it's essential to work on
the following
establishing healthy boundaries
setting healthy boundaries is essential
to maintaining your well-being and
fostering healthy relationships and this
one's really key as well adjusting your
expectations on other people oftentimes
the victim mentality is because we
expect other people to act the way that
we would act if we were them and we get
upset and angry because other people are
not doing what we think they should in
every situation oftentimes you need to
accept other people are not you they're
not going to respond the way that you
would respond as well realize that you
might have a level and a standard on
yourself that you put on yourself that
maybe even trauma and abuse put on you
over the years of having to serve having
to show up at a certain level that
wasn't healthy and then you've ended up
projecting that onto somebody else now I
know that this is a deep topic and I
know that this might bring up some stuff
in you you might even disagree with it
but I'm I'm telling you this has been
the stuff that in my journey for the
last couple of years I have discovered
and have become and that's the third
Point here massively self-aware of is
recognizing my own thoughts feelings and
behaviors for why I keep perpetuating
the victim mindset and listen I'm not
perfect in this area I'm still dealing
with these issues I'm even noticing as
I'm teaching this that I don't fully
Implement what I'm talking about right
now but I know up here in my knower that
I need to start doing these and so I
need to start living this way that I'm
telling you as well
we have to practice mindfulness
journaling engaging in self-reflection
and this is one of the last most
important parts here is open
communication
my wife and I we have found that when we
communicate powerfully the needs of each
other when I talk about what my needs
are what I'm going to do
and and I'm not blaming we're not
assuming that the other person can read
each other's mind
that our communication gets better and
that it doesn't leave room for the
victim mindset to come in to where the
other person is now responsible for how
we're feeling one of the biggest reasons
why many of us don't feel heard don't
feel seen don't feel like we're able to
get the help that we want is we're not
asking for it we're expecting other
people to just know what we need because
bless God we know what other people need
at all times they should do the same
thing right that's standard again that
standard that we're trying to hold other
people to that to be honest they don't
know people can't read your mind the
reason why most people you might be so
aware of what other people need is a
trauma response it comes from you having
to feel like I have to manage and
maintain other people's emotions for
Safety and Security and other people
don't think that way they don't operate
that way
they haven't been through what you've
been through and so expecting them to
operate in the same way with you and
being angry when they don't and feeling
oh they don't love me they don't care
about me
they they clearly don't love me because
they didn't reach out and ask if I
needed help
that's an unreasonable standard and we
need to start to accept
that other people are not us that
they're not going to show up the way
that we show up that we that we might
want them to show up and so you can live
a life of disappointment and anger being
upset that other people are not serving
you the way that you demand
unfortunately
that just creates so much hurt and pain
in relationships or you can start
accepting people for the way that they
are and start communicating start asking
for what you want more often
one of the biggest things I tell people
in the coaching relationship and in
building a coaching business and if
you're listening to this you're a coach
you're a trainer you're a mentor you
can't work harder on your clients goals
than they're willing to work themselves
some coaches out there they will go out
there and they will try to preemptively
know what their clients need at all
times and they create this co-dependent
relationship because that's how they
live their life in all areas of their
life
instead of saying you know what I'm
going to meet you halfway this is the
time that we have boundaries give you
the opportunity to show and demonstrate
to people how you're willing to show up
how you're willing to love how you're
willing to lead and how you're willing
to experience the relationship with
somebody they're not a form of
Separation they're actually a form of
connection
and when you learn that when you learn
that it's about connecting not
separating it makes everything else in
your life so much better
and so listen I hope that this has
encouraged you I hope that this has
given you some ideas to think about ways
that you can improve ways that you can
look at to break free from the victim
mentality like I said
I've been on this journey for a long
time 35 years I've been operating as a
victim
with the victim mentality I'm looking
over what I'm teaching you today and
seeing how I need to grow in some of
these areas myself
still constantly dealing with some of
this stuff
but I'm better than I was yesterday and
we're on a path we're on a journey we're
on this journey together grow your life
everybody we'll talk soon have a good
one